welcome I'm Tom gravity and this is
meditating with her baking I'm a
cognitive psychologist and a cognitive
scientist at the University of Toronto I
study mindfulness scientifically
mindfulness and related phenomena like
flow mystical experiences wisdom etc
I've also been a practitioner of a
person meditation that a contemplation
Tai Chi Chuan and she come for 29 years
and I've been teaching it professionally
introductory classes for almost 20 years
this is a course I mean that means it's
progressive the classes build on each
other Monday and Thursday are teaching
classes today is a is a teaching class
will go till 10:00 after 10:00
if this is your first time joining us I
recommend instead of trying to sit with
us today you're welcome to sit if you
wish but I'm probably be more helpful
because this will be recorded you'll be
able to watch it later at your leisure
go back and watch day one at least and
then you'll see what you missed and then
you can join us tomorrow when we will
sit together so Tuesdays Wednesdays
Friday and Saturdays we just sit
together from 9:00 to 10:00 I do a
review for each class there's a Q&A
section at the end and I'll help you
able to answer your question so as I
said today is a teaching class and what
I want to talk about today is the second
of the core four that we're finding in
order to properly befriend ourselves and
set up an excellent foundation and
platform for the cultivation of
mindfulness and the second of the court
for is finding your root now this is a
particularly influenced by Tai Chi Chuan
so many people come to meditation
because they're very interested in
relaxing and of course that's extremely
central of people's mind right now
because of you know the extra stressors
were facing which are significant but we
have to remember that
they're trying to get a form of a
relaxation that's good for mindfulness a
form of relaxation that will actually
more properly connect us in an adaptive
manner to the world so what I'm trying
to do is get you to see the contrast
between the normal relaxation that we
all understood and to which we are you
know I deeply habituated this is the
drug session you do when you want to
move towards falling asleep right you
start to dull your mind your body
becomes insensitive your awareness of
the world decreases your ability to
monitor and manage your mind decreases
and you pass into unconsciousness and of
course this is tremendously valuable I'm
not criticizing it in any way but that's
not what we want here we don't want a
relaxation that takes us into
mindlessness
we want a relaxation that actually
enhances and takes us deeper into
mindfulness so a good place to look for
that is in the martial arts especially
things like Tai Chi Chuan being what I
call the internal martial arts because
they really have spent a lot of time
working on this kind of this kind of
relaxation relaxation for mindfulness so
if you see like a martial artist they'll
often do something in the tradition I
was taught what's called sort of finding
your root I won't stand out but you know
they sink down and then their arms sink
and you can see that they're kind of
elastic now obviously what they're not
trying to do there is to become
unconscious because that would be
extremely dangerous what are we doing
well the relaxation that we're doing I'm
sort of modeling with my arms or what
they're doing is they're relaxing their
arms because they're trying to get to a
place where they're actually increasing
the sensitivity in their arms in their
hands and they're also trying to find a
place of stability because that
combination of stability and sensitivity
and the kind of position they're taking
is multi out for like transforming this
part you don't fight with this posture
obviously but this posture has you sort
of multiply act really well set to make
the adaptive changes rapidly that you
need to make so there's with rooting
what you're trying to do is where
x2 you find that point of sensitivity
and stability and the tradition astiz
called invitation tradition this is
called being as still as a mountain but
as alert as a warrior and so the martial
art metaphor that I'm using here is
actually appropriate for this tradition
so I'm going to teach you how to find
your route now like before with finding
your Center I will talk you through it
but so don't start doing it right now
let me describe it to you so when I use
certain phrases and terms when I'm
talking you through it you'll understand
what I'm talking about so what I'm going
to ask you to do when we start it is
bring your mind you know tension in your
awareness to the top of your head and
then I'll say wash your attention what
do I mean by wash I mean don't jump your
attention from here to your eyes but
wash your attention awareness to your
eye area okay and then when I get to the
ayah your eye area I'll say I want you
to I want you to pause and look and what
I mean by that is I want you to become
aware of this area any tension any
tightness in detangling you know the
sensations that are here any sense of
any imminent information that's trying
to come into your awareness that we were
normally back rounding or ignoring
because it's not you know super salient
to us and so what we want to do right is
we want to look at it like so
notice the change when you're just
seeing and I ask you to look see what
happens when I ask you right to go from
just seeing me or just seeing the
situation to looking over there right
you're getting that added attention that
is getting you present and coupled to
that area so you know looking you're not
trying to do anything you're not trying
to make yourself feel better there might
be unpleasant sensations there so be it
so you're going to be looking and then
I'll say listening and this is even more
that focusing well you know seeing is
for looking hearing is to listening but
what I try to pick up on that
metaphorically is like when you're at a
party and there's lots of people talking
and you're listening to the person
that's in front of you so what you're
doing is you
creating that special sensitivity
channel for them so you first look and
then you're listening you're really
opening yourself up sensitizing yourself
giving a dedicated channel of awareness
and attention to what's going on now
you're going to do loosen it and so the
loosening here is when you try to relax
the area but this is a crucial point
you're relaxing not to make anything go
away or make anything better you're
loosening because what you're trying to
do is get some stability and sensitivity
you're loosening to enhance the
listening that's the kind of a lack
sation that we're pursuing here and then
I'll say let it flow and what I mean by
that is let it fill your awareness and
it sort of unfold almost like a movie
that's starting to unfold and roll and
let it fill your awareness again you're
not trying to make anything happen
and you're not trying to make you know
bag sensations go away you're trying to
be as deeply present as possible you're
trying to increase sensitivity and yet
remain deeply stable within that
sensitivity so letting it flow and then
letting it go means you're not going to
be attached to this you're not gonna get
too enmeshed in it because then you're
going to let your attention wash you're
going to let sort of this sensation of
opening melting draining letting your
attention and awareness washed your
heart area and then we'll repeat it will
do looking listening loosening letting
it flow letting it go opening melting
draining to the GaN Tien and then open
it and repeating that whole process here
and then down to where you can feel
where you're touching your pillow
touching your chair right and you repeat
it there at that point of contact
because what you're trying to do
especially the point of contact is
really enhance yourself round
this connectedness when the buddha
achieved enlightenment he touched the
earth okay so you're touching the earth
you're grounding this is like the root
of a tree and then what you want to do
is you want to ask you to imagine and
this is imagination we use imagination
this is the sense of imagination not as
imaginary but imaginal we're using
imagination to train perceptions and we
now have some very good problem you're
going to use imagination to enhance that
sense of groundedness by imagining all
of this pooled awareness and attention
and everything that's sort of drained
down like a liquid seeking three feet
below you like the root of a tree
growing right seeking stability seeking
nourishment you through several points
doing a back line taking you all the way
down your back and then we'll leave that
so we'll have a front root a back root
and then we'll do that we'll go through
a center root you want to imagine in the
center of your head right chest abdomen
point of contact is the center front
root a back root and then a center root
and then they all become one root
reaching into the earth and then I'll
ask you to like make any micro
adjustments necessary to get your root
and your sensor that your Center to be
fully integrated together your root is
actually just a deep extension and
development of your being centered so
what we're going to do today is the
following well though they'll be silence
for a bed
everybody will close their eyes will be
silence and I'll give people time to do
the symmetry always Center before your
root I'm teaching you these and in order
for an explicit purpose okay so find
your Center then I'll talk you through
the routing exercise I'll talk you all
the way through it and then when the
routing exercise is done we won't come
out of the exercise what I'll say is you
know savor what it is like to be deeply
centered and rooted and then begin to
meditate follow your breath
the way I've touched so what's gonna
happen one more time
they'll be silenced you'll be centering
there'll be a little bit jarring because
I'll have to then start speaking to you
I'll try and do that as as sort of
gently as possible I will talk you
through the routing exercise back Center
remember looking coming into a coupled
contact listening really sensitizing
yourself loosening relaxing which is
trying to find a increased sensitivity
but a stability within it letting it
flow letting it unfold and deeply talk
to you and then letting it go not
getting attached or immersed and it
meshed in it letting your attention and
awareness open melt drain wash down to
the next area where we stop after I talk
you through the first the front the
second the back the third the center I
will then say now begin after you savor
your enter and your route begin to
meditate okay so that's what we're going
to do so again about it a couple minutes
of silence to begin we'll set the timer
a little bit longer today we'll set the
timer for about 17 minutes let's begin
gently bring your attention and
awareness to the very top of your head
that your attention awareness wash to
your eye area pausing there and we're
looking and to pick up on any tension
tightness emotional tone sensations
imminent information just let it talk to
you looking I'm trying to make anything
happen now listening
no loose Simic relaxing the area but to
enhance the listening and to enhance the
flow of information you're stable within
that flow
now letting it flow really let it feel
and unfold it fills your awareness and
unfolds throughout your mind
now letting it go letting your attention
wash down your throat opening melting
draining if you come to your heart area
stopping in your heart area looking
listening
loosening for the sake of listening
letting it flow
letting it go pension and awareness
washing down to your Dante an area
writer new your naval opening melting
draining to their stopping
loosening for the sake of listening
letting it flow
letting it go opening melting draining
right down to where you feel that point
of contact pausing there looking
listening
loosening for the sake of listening
letting it flow
letting it go opening melting draining
three feet into the earth like the root
of a tree seeking stability seeking
nourishment being deeply grounded
how to leave that running naturally in
place but don't worry about trying to
manage it or maintain it bring your
attention to the top of your head again
very gently don't just jump just go
gently bring you to the top of your head
again washing your attention awareness
over the back of your head opening
melting you training until you get to
the base of your skull point where your
neck goes into your skull lots of
tension there and I'm gonna make all the
tension go away that's not your goal
looking
listening
loosening for listening
letting it flow
letting it go opening melting draining
down the back unit to the base of the
neck spot between the top the tips of
your shoulder blades at the top looking
listening
loosening for listening
letting it flow
letting it go tension awareness opening
melting draining down to about the sin
of your back opposite your solar plexus
stopping there looking
listening
listening for listening
letting it flow
letting it go opening melting draining
all the way down to you feel that point
of contact more towards the back this
time pausing and looking
listening
loosening for the sake of listening
letting it flow
let it get opening melting training
sinking three feet into the earth
the root of a tree singing stability and
nourishment the front rude in your back
root are not touching each other in that
depth connected interwoven
very gently bring your attention
awareness to the top of your head again
opening melting training to an imaginal
space in the very center of your skull
looking
listen
loosening for listening
letting it flow
letting it go opening melting training
spot in the very center of your chest
look
listening
loosening for this
letting it flow
letting it go opening melting dreaming
to a spot in the very center of job
look
listen
loosening for listening
letting it flow
letting it go opening melting draining
making contact of the earth very center
of that contact point now looking
listening
loosening for listening
letting it flow
letting it go training opening melting
trading singing three feet into the
earth like the root of a tree seeking
stability seeking nourishment
groundedness fragrant black root center
and are now one root feel that root as
an extension and development of your
Center to any micro adjustments you feel
that your centromere root are locked
together interwove savor what it's like
to be deeply centered and rooted
now begin to meditate
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best she can to
integrate with your cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition try to
create a sense of what it would be like
to be centered and rooted having that
awareness of your mind as you open your
eyes as you look around what's it like
trying to you're gonna it's gonna fade
into the background let it fade but let
it fade slowly what it's like to be
centered and rooted what it's like to
have that awareness of the patterns and
processes in your mind as you open your
eyes and start to look around try to get
into the habit I'll talk Manti out of
this every time I'm integrating in this
manner practice this integration is
trying to build a bridge between your
practice and your everyday consciousness
and partnership they probably wanted to
sit a little longer but I was trying to
be mindful the fact that it's also a
long time for people that are novices on
their legs and stuff so we hope we
already were sitting for a total of 17
minutes and when you initially are doing
this on your own you'll find that you'll
cut to take quite a bit of time as I
said to you know Center and route and do
the three lines and enter in seconds and
you'll be able to route it sometimes it
takes practice it takes a lot of
dedicated mindful thoughtful careful
okay I'm going to turn to answer some
questions that might you might have any
questions that might have emerged not
only from today but from your previous
practice I'll pick up on a couple that
we didn't get to last time prema asked
is it okay to focus on a sound you're
hearing actually no hearing or listening
to something in your environment is
another distractor so if you're hearing
a sound step back and label it with an
ING word hearing or listening and then
return your attention to your breath
who's that behind me so now I tried to
answer this last time but amar has
suggested that I misunderstood there's
over there there's a portrait it's an
original work of art from Joshua bow or
bow it's his last name is B Oh W II it
conveys self transcendence I'll send a
picture of I'll post a picture of it
behind me on that on the wall is the
little thing that some of you may have
noticed it this is a small relief figure
it's also painted this is a legacy for
my mother she died in 2001 and it's a
near dead figure that's deep and
reflective thought and so I often
understand it as somebody who has taken
up a philosophical way of life and as
cultivating wisdom next question could
you let can you explain the letter flow
part in more detail do you mean
expanding the awareness of that one
location into the space around you um
perhaps but what I meant is more
expanding your awareness within your
that introspective space so that it
fills up it's picking up more and more
of your mind sort of let feel more of
that inner space that you can look
inside and see oh so right if that if
that works for you by sort of meat
letting it expand into sort of a
peripheral awareness so if you're if
you're introspective awareness is sort
of outside of your body in some way then
do it that way but what I'm trying to
get is I'm trying to get you to learn to
enhance your to enhance and integrate
together your interoceptive awareness of
a particular area and your introspective
awareness of what's going on in your
mind if that image that you just
mentioned is helping you to do that then
please do that but that's what I'm
trying to convey with let it flow what
I'm looking and listening is it meant to
be like I would bend over and look like
I'm trying to look under the bed or at
something but only mentally and without
moving yes it's that it's that sort of
exploratory probative use of your
attention to try and zero in focus see
what you're not initially seeing open
yourself
that's exactly correct that's exactly
correct the person who asked that was I
think Nick Lee I just moved his mouth
breathing okay with belly breathing it
seems needed it's a good idea if you can
this is also from crema to not sometimes
your nose is stuffed up and you have to
do mouth breathing when you do that put
your tongue oh bob bit like you're gonna
say pee or duck and hold it there and
breathe over and your moist tongue
because that will help keep your air
passages moist mouth breathing is
generally a bad idea and you're probably
trying to get too much baby breathing so
again try not to force it
give it time it will gently come over
you it's best if you can if your nose is
unplugged to new noise breathing nose
peeping not know he's breathing because
that will help keep your air passages
moist and you'll need that when you
start to meditate for longer periods
Nicolas olymic err why take a day off
each week that the most meditation
courses do that sometimes when you're
not retreat they don't I'm doing that so
I have some dedicated time with for with
my Emily okay
I've always made it a practice that I
unplug on Sunday even from work when I'm
at the University so that's part of my
overall practice that I'm not going to
give up unplugging on Sundays it will be
good for people to have a day where
they're just trying it on their own I
understand that it is very helpful
there's research showing this -
meditating with other people and there's
a figure there it helps you to practice
and that's why the miss for five weeks
is going to be you practicing with other
people but it's good also to put in one
day where you have to see what that will
feel like when you transfer that to
meditating on your own another question
from Victoria if you're in a chair and
you are rooting through the feet or the
pelvis do the the pelvis and then you
could sort of also open and melt through
your feet if you want to extend it so
start with the pelvis as if there was a
root
down there like in a tree but also I'm
open it melt and drain through your legs
and improve include your feet that's a
good question a very good question and
playing with that and see what what
combination works best for giving you
that sense of groundedness and
connectedness to the earth all right so
we're coming to an end of our time
together today we will meet together
tomorrow at ten o'clock
sorry at 9:30 to 10:00 o'clock my
mistake tomorrow is we're just sitting
I'll do a very quick review of what we
did today and then we will sit together
and then there'll be some Q&A at the end
please
I want to thank always Ammar for all
this technical help is invaluable for my
beloved son Jason for his help and him
sitting with me I asked I'm thanking you
for joining me I'm hoping you're finding
this helpful I would ask you please to
surprise subscribe to my channel because
that way you can be notified of the next
video you can get connections to some of
the other relevant videos where I talk
about mindfulness I talked about the
cultivation of wisdom the video series
that I've mentioned a few times I'm
asking you to please subscribe to my
channel as I mentioned we're doing this
every Sunday morning sorry every morning
except Sunday morning every morning
except Sunday morning at 9:30
alright so please remember continuity of
practice more important than quantity
keep up your practice
I hope it's serving you well and I'll
see you all tomorrow at 9:30 thank you
very much for your time and attention
you